A Finding Aid to the Louise Nevelson Papers, circa 1903-1988, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Art Work, 1905-1982; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 13, 20, 40, Sol 43; 0.5 linear feet)
  - Drawings, Period Furniture, 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 42)
    Includes negatives and copy prints made by AAA for some.
  - Watercolors, Miscellaneous, 1922-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 43)
    Includes a 1922 watercolor on board that may or may not be a self-portrait.
  - Watercolors, Still Life of Eggs in a Bowl, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Watercolors, Flowers, 1929?; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Drawings, [Scenes of Europe?], undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Printing Plates, undated; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - Oversize, Watercolors and Drawings, Old Masters, 1916; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 13, F40) (Box 20)
  - Ralph Rosenborg Sketchbook, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Teddy Haseltine, 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Tapestry from Colette, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 8-9)
  - Pierce, Waldo, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Art from Others, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Art from Others, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Illustrated Holiday and Greeting Cards, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 12-14)
  - Birthday Card from Marisol Escobar, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 15)
  - Louise Nevelson: Geometry + Magic (1982), Diana MacKown and Rawn Fulton, Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (Betacam) Copy; 1 Film reel 16 mm (Box 43, Folder 4)
- Photographs, circa 1903-1980s; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 14-15, 20, OV 29, 40-41, Sol 43; 3.5 linear feet)
  Series consists of photographs of Nevelson as well as her family and freinds, studio, exhibits, and art work.
  The Photographs series is arranged into six subseries:
  9.1: Family and Personal, circa 1903-1930s
  9.2: Artist, circa 1955-1979
  9.3: Exhibitions and Installations, 1959-1979
  9.4: Art Work, 1940s-1970s
  9.5: Slides, 1950s-1970s
  9.6: Photographs from Farnsworth Art Museum, 1908-1980s
  The bulk of this series has been scanned, except for negatives, photographs of art work, slides, and donated images from the Farnsworth Art Museum.
  - Family and Personal, circa 1903-1930s; 9.1; Archival Resource Key
    Subseries consists of photographs of the Berliawsky family, including what seems to be a portrait of Nevelson's grandparents and their sons presumably dating from the late 1800s, a portrait of her father, Isaac Berliawsky circa 1903-1904, a portrait of the Berliawsky family after their arrival in America (including Nevelson and her siblings) circa 1907, and a portrait of Nevelson's sister, Anita Berliawsky, as a young woman; Nevelson's class and team photographs, including class photographs from 1913 and 1918 (the year in which she graduated) and a photograph of Nevelson on the basketball team; portraits of Nevelson as a young girl; photographs of the Nevelson family, including a portrait of her husband, Charles, a photograph of Nevelson with her husband and his brothers, and photographs of Nevelson with her husband and son; photographs of her son, Mike, as a baby and young man; and photographs of Nevelson in New York circa 1922, in Munich circa 1931, on board a ship to Paris in 1932, and sometime during the 1930s, before she became known as an artist.
    Most files contain copy prints and negatives of the photographs made by AAA. Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Berliawsky Family, circa 1903-1907, and undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Class and Team Photographs, 1913-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Portraits of Louise Nevelson as a Young Girl, circa 1915-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Nevelson Family, 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Mike Nevelson, 1920s-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Louise Nevelson, circa 1922-1930s; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Oversize, Louise Nevelson, circa 1922-1930s; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F6) (Box 20)
  - Artist, circa 1955-1979, undated; 9.2; Archival Resource Key
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson once she had become known, and began to be honored, as an artist. The majority are either portraits of the artist or photographs of the artist at work, at home, and in different settings taken by various individuals. Most notable among these are the portraits of Nevelson and photographs of her house and studio on Thirtieth Street taken by Jeremiah Russell and the photographs of Nevelson at home and in her studio, at work with her assistant Diana Mackown, and with her art work taken by Ugo Mulas, the Italian photographer known for documenting the life and work of artists. Others, including the portraits taken by Renate Ponsold and Jack Mitchell, may have been used in various art works and/or exhibitions; still others, such as the photographs taken by Basil Langton, may have been intended for publication. Also found are photographs of Nevelson at various exhibitions and openings (including the opening of her show at Studio Marconi in Milan, Italy), at various social gatherings (including a reception at her brother's hotel, the Thorndike Hotel, where she was photographed with Andrew Wyeth), and receiving various awards and honors (including honorary degrees from Columbia University and Smith College, and the first Women's Caucus for Art Award). Also included are photographs from the artist, Robert Indiana, featuring himself in front of his and Nevelson's sculptures, and at gatherings with Nevelson, and some photographs that were featured in Look magazine.
    Photographs are arranged into files according to photographer, type, or subject. Files are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Portrait by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 20 and OV 29) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson's House and Studio on Thirtieth Street by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson (negatives without prints), 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders; see also Box 20 and OV 29) (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Ugo Mulas, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders; see also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 13-15)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson at Various Exhibitions and Openings, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 14, Folder 16-19)
    - Portraits, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 20)
      Includes ones by Marie Cosindas, Jack Mitchell, and others.
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson at Various Gatherings, 1969-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 21-22)
    - Photographs from Robert Indiana, 1971, 1973; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 23-25)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson Receiving Various Awards and Honors, 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 26-27)
    - Portraits, Self-Portrait, and Art Work Photograph by Arnie Zane, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Portraits by Renate Ponsold, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Basil Langton, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson for Look Magazine, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs (relating to but not featuring Nevelson), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F10-12) (Box 20)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Ugo Mulas, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F13-15) (Box 20)
    - Oversize, Portraits, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F20) (Box 20)
    - Oversize, Portrait by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F7) (Oversize 29)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F10-12) (Oversize 29)
  - Exhibitions and Installations, 1959-1979; 9.3; Archival Resource Key
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson's art work in various exhibitions and on display in various locations. Included are photographs of an exhibition at the Martha Jackson Gallery (October-November, 1959) and of a retrospective at the Whitney Museum in 1979, as well as of a Nevelson work on display at the Tate Gallery; and a photograph album of her one-man show at the Minami Gallery, Tokyo, Japan in 1975. Other photographs include ones of Nevelson's work displayed in the Thorndike Hotel (owned by her brother) and the Queens College library; and ones of Nevelson's outdoor (metal) sculptures installed at Wichita State University, Yale University, and in Italy, as well as ones of a Nevelson wood sculpture in an outdoor setting (not necessarily an outdoor sculpture).
    Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Exhibition at Martha Jackson Gallery, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Nevelson Work in the Tate Gallery, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Various and Unidentified Exhibitions, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Indoor Installations and Displays, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Outdoor Installation and Displays, 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Photograph Album, Exhibition at Minami Gallery (Tokyo, Japan), 1975; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Retrospective at the Whitney Museum, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Oversize, Outdoor Installations and Displays, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F37) (Box 20)
    - Oversize, Photograph Album, Exhibition at Minami Gallery (Tokyo, Japan), 1975; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 14, F38) (Box 20)
  - Art Work, 1940s-1970s; 9.4; Archival Resource Key
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson's art work (primarily works in terra cotta, tattistone, and wood, as well as some drawings and paintings). Also included are scattered photographs of paintings by Louis Eilshemius (amongst the ones taken by John Schiff and Jeremiah Russell) and Ralph Rosenborg that Nevelson owned. At least some of the photographs by Schiff seem to have been created for the Nierendorf Gallery; photographs by Russell were likely created for Nevelson; photographs by Buckley Semley, Oliver Baker, and Rudy Burckhardt seem to have been created for the Martha Jackson Gallery (some of these, especially the ones by Semley, may have been used in the inventory of Nevelson's art work carried out by her assistants and gallery staff). Photographs of Nevelson's art work are typically undated, most lack any identifying information, and many are duplicates. Numbers on the verso of some seem to correspond to the art work pictured, however there is no further information about what exactly the number is meant to reference or signify.
    Photographs are arranged in files according to photographer. Photographs of various works, art work by Ralph Rosenborg, and unidentified art work are arranged in separate files at the end of the series. Even though most photographs are undated, dates provided represent the decade in which the photographs were most likely created. Files are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Photographs by John Schiff, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Photographs by John Schiff, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 41-42)
      (2 folders; not scanned)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (8 folders; not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 43-50)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, Negatives, 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 51-53)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, Negatives, 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Photographs by Buckley Semley, 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 5-11)
    - Photographs by Oliver Baker, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Photographs by Oliver Baker, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Photographs by Rudy Burckhardt, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Photographs by Rudy Burckhardt, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Photographs by Rudy Burckhardt, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Photographs by Tom Kendall, late 1950s; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Various Nevelson Works of Art, 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 19-20)
    - Various Nevelson Works of Art (negatives), undated; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Works of Art by Ralph Rosenborg, undated; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified Art Work, undated; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Slides, 1950s-1970s; 9.5; Archival Resource Key
    Subseries consists of glass slides and transparencies of Nevelson and her art work. The photographs on these slides typically do not duplicate those found amongst the artist and art work photographs above. Included are glass slides of photographs taken by Dorothy Dehner, primarily documenting the works of art in the rooms, studio, and garden of Nevelson's house on Thirtieth Street. Dehner's photographs also feature Nevelson at work and posed in front of certain works, outside views of the house, and the Eilshemius paintings and pre-Columbian sculptures owned by Nevelson. Dehner took the photographs on successive trips to Nevelson's house. The slides appear to be numbered in various sequences, perhaps corresponding to each trip. However, at this point, all the slides have been mixed together and it is difficult to reconstruct any meaningful order from the numbers.
    Also included are various slides of Nevelson and her art work dating from the 1950s; slides of art work dating from circa 1961, three of which seem to have been used by Tom Kendall in a lecture; slides of Nevelson and her assistant in front of her house, and ones of Nevelson alone in her house and studio dating from the mid-1960s; slides featuring Nevelson posing in front of her art work, at home and in her studio, in her neighborhood, and at a foundry, and slides featuring different views of various outdoor installations of her metal sculptures, all of which date from the 1970s; and glass slides of Nevelson art work, along with some negatives.
    Slides are undated; however the dates provided represent the decade in which they were most likely created. Slides are arranged according to type and photographer or subject of photograph.
    - Glass Slides of Photographs by Dorothy Dehner, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 16; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Slides of Artist and Art Work Photographs, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Slides of Art Work Photographs, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Slides of Artist Photographs, 1964; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Slides of Artist and Installation Photographs, 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous Glass Slides of Art Work Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders; see also Box 16; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 29-30)
    - Copy Prints and Negatives Made by AAA, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 31-32)
    - Glass Slides of Photographs by Dorothy Dehner, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 15, F24; not scanned) (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous Glass Slides of Art Work Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 16)
  - Photographs from Farnsworth Art Museum, 1908-1980s; 9.6; Archival Resource Key
    Images of Nevelson with family and friends, portraits of the artist, events and social gatherings, Nevelson's exhibits and installations, her home and studio, as well as her art work.
    Arrangement
    The photographs are arranged in rough chronological order and by type.
    - Farnsworth Photography Inverntory, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - Nevelson Family and Personal Images, 1908-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 17-18)
    - Events and Social Gatherings, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 19-23)
    - Events and Social Gatherings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Portraits of Nevelson, 1919-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 24-25)
    - Portraits of Nevelson, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Nevelson Home and Studio, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 40, Folder 26)
    - Nevelson's Assistants, Diana MacKown and Ted Haseltine, circa 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - "Interiors" Series by Diana MacKown, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Nierendorf Gallery Images from Nevelson's First Solo Show, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Nevelson Installations in Public Spaces, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 3-4)
    - Farnsworth Museum Exhibit and Trip to Rockland, Maine, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 5-8)
    - Visit to Farnsworth Museum, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Installation from B.R. Kornblatt Gallery, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Nevelson Art, 1915-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Nevelson Art, 1915-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 12-13)
    - Nevelson Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Nevelson Slide Show, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Laurie Lisle Photographs for Nevelson Book, 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Wood Gathering Project for Nevelson, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 41, Folder 17)
- Unprocessed Addition, 2019; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 40.5 Megabytes
  There is a 40.5 MB unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2022 that includes digital photographs of a plaque commemoration installed in Louise Nevelson's birth town of Pereyaslav, Ukraine in 2019. Organizers of the event include Julie Gard, Associate Professor of Writing and Associate Director of the Writing Center at the University of Wisconsin-Superior; Yuri Avramenko, Memorial Organizer in Pereyaslav-Ukraine and Maria Nevelson, Founder and Executive Director and Chair of the Board for the Louise Nevelson Foundation. Materials date from 2019.
  - Unprocessed Digital Photographs, Archival Resource Key